Finding Aid for Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records, 1956-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Computer Sales Program 1986-1993
  - “Kickoff”
    - 1989 (Box 58)
      (CRLT: MICROS discussion Kickoff Pricing, Truckload Sale, IBM Promo)
    - 1990 (Box 58)
    - 1992 (Box 58)
    - 1993 (Box 58)
  - “Mac Truck,” 1986-1987 (Box 58)
    (includes paper on Background and History of Sales Program at Michigan)
  - MicroSales Group 1986-1987 (Box 58)
  - NeXt 1989 (Box 58)
  - Ongoing Sales 1992 (Box 58)
  - Paper Personal Computer Sales at the University of Michigan: Questions/Concerns Regarding the University’s Microcomputer Sales Program Notes to the Computer Kickoff ’89 Income Statement and The Computer Kickoff ’89 (preliminary) Income Statement, January 11, 1990 (Box 58)
  - Procedures Handbook for Dealers, not dated (Box 58)
  - Review of Operations Consultant Report by Plante & Moran June 1985 (Box 58)
  - Unix Kickoff 1990 (Box 58)
  - Zenith Pricing 1988-1989 (Box 58)
- Computing Sites 1985-1994
  The Computing Sites (2.25 linear feet, 1985-1994) series reveals the tremendous increase in the demand by faculty and students for computing technology on campus. This almost sudden demand, created by the introduction of the desktop computer in the mid-1980s, is evident in the materials within this series. By the early 1990s, the lines outside the largest computing site, Angell Hall, snaked down the hallway every evening. Students found themselves waiting two or more hours just to use a computer for word processing. Interesting documentation printed excerpts from the CONFER (online discussion) hosted on MEET:STUDENTS More Computers Needed! and a flurry of electronic mail messages sent to Doug Van Houweling by irate students accompanied by a petition signed by over 800 students for longer hours at Angell Hall. Parallel to the growth of the computing sites services, a project designed to reach out to students in the residence halls was started in 1985. One of the first university residential computing programs in the country, ResComp, combined computer access with consulting support to over 14,000 students. Included in this series is the Proposal for Study of Residential Hall Computing Project and Impact of Information Technology on Undergraduates, presented at the Residence Hall Computing Program Symposium in 1988. The series does include documentation most of the other campus computing sites such as NUBS, 611 Church Street, but is strongest for Angell Hall and ResComp.
  - 611 Church Street
    - 1987 (Box 58)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 58)
  - Advance Workstation Support
    - 1988 (Box 58)
    - 1989 (Box 58)
  - Angell Hall
    - 1985 (Box 58)
    - 1988 (Box 58)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 58)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 58)
    - Apple Computer 1988-1990 (Box 59)
    - Renovation Plan June 30, 1994 (Box 59)
  - Baits Hall 1986 (Box 59)
  - Biological Station 1989-1990 (Box 59)
  - Card Key System 1991-1992 (Box 59)
  - CONFER Discussion in MEET:STUDENTS More Computers Needed!, 1992 (Box 59)
  - Couzens Hall 1986 (Box 59)
  - Computer Cluster Agreements 1985-1986 (Box 59)
  - Chemistry Department
    - 1988-1990 (Box 59)
    - 1991 (Box 59)
  - East Quad 1987 (Box 59)
  - Expense Breakdown 1989-1990 (Box 59)
  - Fletcher Hall 1986 (Box 59)
  - Graduate Library 1991-1992 (Box 59)
  - Hours 1987 (Box 59)
  - Hours and Petition 1990, 2 folders (Box 59)
  - International Business Machine (IBM) Equipment 1989-1990 (Box 59)
  - IBM Proposal Meeting 1988-1989 (Box 59)
  - Lawyer’s Club 1986 (Box 59)
  - Law School 1990-1992 (Box 59)
  - Learning Resources Center 1985 (Box 59)
  - Manager's Planning Binder
    - 1984 (Box 59)
    - 1985 (Box 59)
  - Markley Hall 1986 (Box 59)
  - Martha Cook 1985-1986 (Box 59)
  - Mason Hall Classrooms 1989 (Box 59)
  - Michigan Union 1993-1994 (Box 60)
  - Mosher Jordan Hall 1987 (Box 60)
  - Music School 1985-1989 (Box 60)
  - New University Hospital 1987 (Box 60)
  - North Campus Commons 1990 (Box 60)
  - North University Building Station (NUBS) 1989 (Box 60)
  - Paper Getting Out of the Computer Center: Where the Students Are, September 1986 (Box 60)
  - Presentation Discovering and Developing Innovative Technological Applications in Student Affairs, March 16, 1990 (Box 60)
  - Proposal A Proposal for Study of Residential Hall Computing Project, circa 1985 (Box 60)
  - Public Facilities Status Reports 1986-1987 (Box 60)
  - Report A Report of the Literature, Science and Arts (LS&A) Advisory Committee on Computing, June 1, 1984 (Box 60)
  - ResComp
    - Advisory Meetings 1988-1989 (Box 60)
    - Coordinator Meeting Minutes 1987 (Box 60)
    - Funding Issues 1989-1991 (Box 60)
    - Housing Division 1986-1989 (Box 60)
    - Paper
      - Residence Hall Computing Program Symposium: Impact of Information Technology on Undergraduates, March 1988 (Box 60)
    - Proposal
      - Proposal for Housing and Residence Hall Computing Network, March 20, 1990 (Box 60)
      - A Proposal to Apple Computer, Inc. for Partial Funding of the Residence Hall Computing Program (ResComp) at the University of Michigan circa 1986 (Box 60)
    - Resale Program 1989 (Box 60)
    - Operations Manual circa 1987 (Box 60)
    - Residence Hall Libraries 1989 (Box 60)
    - Statement of Goals and Objectives 1988-1989 (Box 60)
    - Statistics 1988-1989 (Box 60)
  - Schools and Colleges circa 1985-1986 (Box 60)
  - School of Art and Architecture (Computer) Laboratory and Library
    - 1985-1986 (Box 60)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 60)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 60)
  - School of Education Instructional Lab 1986-1987 (Box 60)
  - College of Literature, Science and Arts Math Lab 1990 (Box 60)
  - School of Natural Resources 1985 (Box 60)
  - School of Nursing 1985 (Box 60)
  - School of Public Health 1985-1988 (Box 60)
  - Services 1991-1992 (Box 60)
  - South Quad Network 1988-1989 (Box 60)
  - Undergraduate Library, Academic Resource Center 1984-1986 (Box 60)
  - UNYN/NUBS 1989-1991 (Box 60)
  - Usage Statistics
    - 1990 (Box 60)
    - 1993 (Box 60)
  - West Quad 1988-1989 (Box 60)
  - Workstation Labs 1990 (Box 60)
- Dean's Partnership Program 1991-1998
  The Dean’s Partnership Program (1 linear foot, 1991-1998) series is comprised of materials from the model partnership forged between ITD and the College of Literature, Science and the Arts in 1991. The Dean’s program essentially sought both to prioritize and customize the specific technology needs for each academic unit during a crucial transition from centralized to distributed computing. While the program was designed to customize needs, there were several common technology related issues facing academic units. Common needs included assistance in migrating data and procedures from the Michigan Terminal System to a client/server infrastructure; workstation configuration; faculty desktop computing; and departmental network development and training. Partnership agreements in this series include “contracts” signed off under Vice Provost Doug Van Houweling and Chief Information Officer Jose-Marie Griffith.
  - Background Materials 1992-1994 Budget Working Group, 1994-1996 (Box 61)
  - College of Architecture 1994-1998 (Box 61)
  - College of Engineering 1990-1994 (Box 61)
  - College of Pharmacy 1994-1995 (Box 61)
  - Digital Futures 1997 (Box 61)
  - Division of Kinesiology 1994-1996 (Box 61)
  - Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1993-1995 (Box 61)
  - Information Technology Division (ITD) Status Reports
    - 1994 (Box 61)
    - 1995 (Box 61)
    - 1996 (Box 61)
  - Information Technology Division (ITD) and School of Literature, Science and Arts UNIX Support Progress Reports 1992-1993 (Box 61)
  - Institute for Public Policy 1994-1996 (Box 61)
  - Law School 1994-1996 (Box 61)
  - Learning Resource Center (LRC) 1991-1992 (Box 61)
  - Medical School 1993-1998 (Box 61)
  - Partnership Definition Document: Instructional Technology Components of Information Technology Division Partnerships with Schools and Colleges, March 29, 1995 (Box 61)
  - Responses to Dean’s Issues March 1994 (Box 61)
  - School of Art 1991-1998 (Box 61)
  - School of Business Administration 1997 (Box 61)
  - School of Dentistry 1994-1995 (Box 61)
  - School of Education 1995-1996 (Box 61)
  - School of Information 1997 (Box 61)
  - College of Literature, Science and the Arts 1990-1995 (Box 61)
  - School of Music 1991-1995 (Box 61)
  - School of Natural Resources 1998 (Box 61)
  - School of Nursing 1992-1995 (Box 61)
  - School of Public Health 1991-1998 (Box 61)
  - School of Social Work 1994 (Box 61)
- Software 1987-1994
  The Series Software (.5 linear feet, 1987-1994) includes materials on software packages selected and purchase by the university mainly for use within the computing sites. The series provides a glimpse of the then popular software applications such as HyperCard, Claris, Mac Write and Write Now.
  - 1987-1994
    - Chipendale (Sociology 231) 1987-1988 (Box 66)
    - Claris 1989 (Box 66)
    - DOS Excel 1989 (Box 66)
    - HyperCard 1987-1988 (Box 66)
    - Internet Access Kits circa 1994 (Box 66)
    - Kodak 1392 printer analysis paper, October 4, 1991 (Box 66)
    - MacTCP License 1989 (Box 66)
    - MacWrite 4.6 1988-1989 (Box 66)
    - Microsoft “Personal Support Project,” 1992 (Box 66)
    - NCARGraphics 1988 (Box 66)
    - Novell Proposal 1989 (Box 66)
    - PCTIE 1988-1989 (Box 66)
    - Software Library 1988 (Box 66)
    - SPSS Support Documentation 1989 (Box 66)
    - Statistical Software Packages 1986-1988 (Box 66)
    - Software Support Discussion 1987-1988 (Box 66)
    - Word Processing Selection Committee 1987 (Box 66)
    - WriteNow 1988 (Box 66)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (3 linear ft. in 4 boxes, 1956-1997), accessioned in 2004/2005, nicely complement the ITD record group as the photographs document much of the evolution and history of the Information Technology Division. Photographs have been divided into four subseries: Computing, Events, People and Organizations, and Systems and Networks.
  - Computing
    The Computing subseries (0.4 linear ft.) illustrates ITD’s role in computing on campus. Here, one can find ITD artwork for campus publications and brochures as well as mockups for an early identification card. More extensively, this series documents the north campus computing center, with drawings and photographs of the building of the computing center to the move of the machine room to the first floor in 1983. Many of the computing center photographs also show students and faculty using computers as well as many photos of computing center staff and networks and systems. Researchers can also find photographs of the 1997 orientation in a binder in Box 64 that includes photographs of Rescomp sites and activities. This subseries also documents the various computing events and activities held by ITD or sponsored by ITD including photographs of the 1971 Computing Center dedication and the Computing Center’s 20th anniversary in 1979. Photographs of various tech fairs in the 1980s can be found here as well as extensive documentation of the 1989 EDUCOM conference in Ann Arbor.
    - Artwork
      - Miscellaneous and general (Box 67)
      - ID card mockups (Box 67)
    - Computing Center
      - Drawings (Box 67)
      - Miscellaneous views (people, dedication, systems, etc.) (Box 67)
      - Move of the machine room to the first floor 1983 (Box 67)
      - People and other views of the center (Box 67)
      - Satellite dishes (Box 67)
    - People using computers (Box 67)
    - Annual computer kick-off sale 1991 (Box 67)
    - Computing Center dedication October 15, 1971 (Box 67)
    - Computing Center 20th anniversary December 5, 1979
      - Photographs (Box 67)
      - Posters, programs, invitations (Box 67)
    - Educom 1989
      - Alumni center, HQ/registration (Box 67)
      - Exhibits and displays (Box 67)
      - General sessions and meetings (Box 67)
      - Pre-conference meeting (Box 67)
      - InfoNet deployment (Box 67)
      - InfoNet/terminals in use (Box 67)
      - Signage and banners (Box 67)
      - Special events and exhibits (Box 67)
      - Text, maps, sites, etc. (Box 67)
    - IBM 3090 celebration (Box 67)
    - Reception for the opening of the UNYN station, February 1983(?) (Box 67)
    - Tech Fair
      - 1981 or 1982 (Box 67)
      - 1983 (Box 67)
      - 1985 (Box 67)
      - Captions (Box 67)
      - Unidentified event (Box 67)
  - People and Organizations
    The People and Organizations subseries (0.2 linear ft.) includes portraits and photographs of staff and administrators of ITD, including major figures in the development of ITD like Eric Aupperle, Carolyn Autrey-Hunley, Robert Bartels, and Doug Van Houweling. Researchers may also want to consult the history folder in the Systems and Networks series, which includes many photographs of important and influential ITD staff.
    - Aupperle, Eric (Box 67)
    - Autrey-Hunley, Carolyn (Box 67)
    - Bartels, Robert (Box 67)
    - Managerial and administrative individuals (Box 67)
    - Miscellaneous and general (Box 67)
    - Van Houweling, Doug (Box 67)
  - Systems/Networks
    The Systems and Networks series (0.5 linear ft.) contains photographs of many of the different systems and networks used throughout ITD’s history including photographs of several different [versions] of IBM and Amdahl machines, MTS and Merit photographs, various network diagrams and graphs, as well as keyboard diagrams for several machines. Of special note is the History folder, which contains photographs and captions used for a display on the history of ITD and computing. These photographs, some dating from the 1950s, nicely illustrate the history and evolution of the various ITD systems and networks to the 1980s.
    - History (Box 68)
    - AMDAHL
      - 470 (Box 68)
      - 580 (Box 68)
      - Equivalent CPU hours/month graphs
        - 1978 (Box 68)
        - 1980 (Box 68)
    - CDC mainframe (Box 68)
    - CRISP (Box 68)
    - Data concentrator (Box 68)
    - IBM
      - 029 card punch (Box 68)
      - 360/67
        - General (Box 68)
        - Diagrams and prints (Box 68)
      - 650 (Box 68)
      - 709 (Box 68)
      - 3090 installation, 1986 (Box 68)
    - Keyboard/keypunch diagrams
      - Editor (Box 68)
      - Ontel (Box 68)
      - Tab 310 (Box 68)
      - Terminals (Box 68)
    - Merit
      - General (Box 68)
      - Network diagrams (Box 68)
      - NSFNET (Box 68)
    - Michigan Terminal System (MTS)
      - General (Box 68)
      - Optical MTS and FORTRAN card graph (Box 68)
      - Machine configuration (Box 68)
      - Timeline (Box 68)
    - Ontel (Box 68)
      (see also keyboard/keypunch diagrams)
    - PDP, CC & data concentrators (Box 68)
    - Tape drive (Box 68)
    - Underground wire/network installation (Box 68)
    - Uninterruptable power source construction (Box 68)
  - Miscellaneous Slides and Photos
    The Miscellaneous Photos consists of several binders of slides and photographs compiled by ITD. These binders have been preserved as accessioned, therefore these images encompass many of the above series. Researchers may find images of people, events, systems, and computing in these binders.
    - Miscellaneous Binders and Slides, 4 folders (Box 68)
    - Unmatched negatives (all years) (Box 68)
    - Oversized-unidentified (Box 68)
    - People/Organization: EDUCOM portraits (Speakers portraits?) (Box 69)
    - Slides and photographs of buildings, people, events, systems circa 1986, undated, 2 volumes (Box 69)
    - IT Communications Networking, Telephones, Staff 1970/1980s (Information Technology Central Services) (Box 69)
    - Slides of Computing Sites and Facilities circa 1986, undated (Box 69)
      (stored in slide boxes; also includes DVDs of slide scans)
Related Material
Computing Center (University of Michigan) records
University Committee on Computer Policy and Utilization (University of Michigan) records
Logic of Computers Group (University of Michigan) records
Inter-University Consortium for Political and Social Research (University of Michigan) records
Arthur W. Burks (University of Michigan) papers
Bernard Galler (University of Michigan) papers
Aaron Finerman (University of Michigan) papers